so the first question is how would you
define self-deception and how is that
different from say cognitive dissonance
okay well we'll start with the first one
how would you define self-deception well
in most accounts of self-deception most
accounts of self-deception have been
basically formulated by logicians
and the logicians make a presumption and
the presumption is essentially that
people think in in fully articulated
statements propositions you might say
and as soon as you accept that you've
run into the paradoxes of self-deception
so for example it doesn't necessarily
seem possible to believe proposition a
and proposition B at the same time so
those would be stable propositions if
they conflict with one another but that
begs a number of questions and one is
first whether or not people think in
propositions in fully articulated
propositions which they do but it's not
the only way they think and then also
what does it mean for two things to
conflict so I'm gonna start with the
second answering the second question
first
so often when I've read badly written
essays often undergraduate essays one of
the things that occurs very frequently
is that the writer will make a statement
on page one or paragraph one and then
two paragraphs later write a statement
that directly contradicts the first
statement and because their thinking is
confused because they're young and
because they don't know how to write and
aren't particularly careful they don't
notice that the two propositions
actually are a logical conflict and one
of the things that indicates is that
people actually don't know this when
things are in logical conflict because
there's no marker for that the only time
people notice that their their
presuppositions about the world are in
conflict is when they try to act out two
contradictory notions at the same time
and find out that acting one out
interferes with acting
another out and sometimes that happens
because they're in conflict with
themselves but even more often it
happens because they become they enter
into conflict with someone else so you
might say that you don't even notice
your propositional conflicts until you
act them out in the world stops you okay
so so you can you can you can maintain
contradictory cognitions endlessly
without ever noticing how disorganized
you are because the world doesn't slap
you in the face for your foolishness
unless you try to act those things out
so the idea that self-deception is
impossible because people can't hold two
contradictory propositions
simultaneously that's completely
ridiculous people do that all the time
so then that's the answer to the second
question and the answer to the first
question is the way that people
generally deceive themselves is that
they act out a series of propositions so
say a series of beliefs about the world
or even one belief about the world and
then they run into evidence that that
enacted belief is not having the result
desired so let's say you tell a joke at
a party and no one laughs and your
proposition was that the joke was funny
and obviously the world indicated to you
that something about that proposition
was faulty now the problem is in part
that the world doesn't tell you which
part of that proposition is wrong it
just tells you that the frame of
reference that you were using when you
were telling the joke had something
wrong had something about it
that was sufficiently erroneous so that
you didn't get the result that was
intended but that subject all sorts of
potential interpretations and so that's
that's a situation where a classic
situation where the the data which is
the outcome of your joke is
insufficiently
infirmity to precisely indicate to you
where that your mistake was made so it's
subject to all sorts of potential
interpretations and one interpretation
could be all these people at this party
are too stupid to understand my humor
and that's a perfectly reasonable
proposition although it's unlikely to be
true
now generally what people do when they
deceive themselves is that they they lay
forth a belief in the world and the
results aren't what they intended and
that produces a negative emotional state
and the negative emotional state
indicates an error but then there's a
whole process of exploration that has to
occur to precisely specify the error and
to precisely specify how the information
about the error could be used to revamp
the whole propositional sequence and
that takes a tremendous amount of work
like a ridiculous amount of work because
let's say people don't laugh at your
jokes
well why is that well maybe you're
hanging around with the wrong sort of
people or maybe your jokes just aren't
that funny or maybe you're kind of a
jerk or maybe you don't know anything
about social interaction and all of
those possibilities emerge when your
joke falls flat and in order for you to
fully investigate the consequences of
that you have to do a tremendous amount
of cognitive work and so generally what
happens is that people just don't do the
work and then what they do is they they
they have as a representation of their
failure what you might describe as what
you might describe as an encounter with
chaos and the encounter is negative
emotion emergency preparation and then
complete indeterminacy as to the
propositional nature of the information
now if you do that enough times so you
lay out your belief and they fail and
you get a negative emotional response
personally but you fail to engage in the
difficult process of exploration to
specify exactly what went wrong what
will happen is that you'll collect
around yourself an absolute morass of
chaos
an indeterminate experience and that's
the place that you will end up living
and that's what self-deception really
looks like it doesn't look like you
believe a and B at the same time and you
know you you don't notice it's way more
complicated than that and I would say
that's akin to cognitive dissonance but
the explanation that I just provided is
far more thorough than the typical
explanation of cognitive dissonance so
so that's an answer to Mike's question
how would you define self-deception and
how is that different from cognitive
dissonance so one of the things you guys
might want to do is type more than one
question don't wait to type a few and
then I can select from there's people in
the room with me here so which would be
the case under normal circumstances but
we're just testing this so any other
questions do you think some people seek
out drama eg they make things difficult
for themselves because they confuse it
with meaning yes people do that all the
time is it because they confuse it with
meaning yes partly that's that's a
really complicated question that you're
asking
the problem with okay so so imagine that
you gave people a choice and the choice
could be that they could suffer stupidly
or they could live a meaningful life and
so you might say well obviously they're
gonna pick leave living a meaningful
life but it's not so obvious because one
of the prices that you pay for living a
meaningful life is that you have to
adopt responsibility and the
responsibility that's attendant on
living a meaningful life might is is
theoretically without limit so for
example one of the ways that's being
conceptualized in classic Christianity
is that in order to lead a meaningful
life you have to take the world sins
onto yourself and that means that you
have to see inside yourself
all of the negative potentialities that
are characterized that being human is
characterized by and then you have to
take responsibility for addressing those
and so when Carl Jung talked about this
for example you know one of the points
he made was that if you do a thorough
enough investigation into your own
faults then you end up scouring what's
the word it's not scouring precisely
harrowing he'll litter as close to
literally as you might imagine and of
course that's a very very very
unpleasant experience and so then you
might say well people are going to
perfectly well and logically want to
avoid that and then they do that using
all sorts of subterfuge because they
don't want to admit to themselves that
they're not taking any responsibility so
they'll often generate false crises in
their own life and amplified problems
beyond necessity so that they can
convince themselves that when they're
effortfully struggling through all that
mess that they're actually taking
responsibility for their lives but
they're not and so so that's one of the
reasons that people might seek out drama
and make things difficult for themselves
and it's partly because they confuse it
with meaning but you know there's
multiple levels of horrible self
deception and confusion and avoidance
that go along with that what rule do you
think diagnosis should play in clinical
practice oh that's easy you need it to
to get reimbursed by insurance providers
and that's about it I shouldn't say that
because that's just people facile
there's a bunch of there's a variety of
functions diagnosis place part of part
of engaging in the process of diagnosis
is utilizing classification and you need
to utilize stable classifications for a
number of reasons one of them is that
you can't understand anything about what
you're dealing with
without classifying it and even if you
classify it incorrectly that might be
better than not classifying at all
because once it's classified incorrectly
you might at least be able to notice
specifically what's incorrect about the
classification and then rectify it which
is to say that a bad theory might be
better than no theory at all
but diagnosis also helps you identify
potential pathways forward so for
example if you diagnose someone is agra
phobic then you have access to the large
wealth of treatment protocols that have
already been developed for agra phobia
and that's very useful
it helps you rule out other things and
that that can be extremely important
because sometimes someone will come to
see you in the clinical practice and
they're just overwhelmed by what's
happening to them and what that means is
that they're in chaos they're suffering
and they have no idea why and then you
could say well yeah what's happening to
you is horrible but it's precisely this
kind of horrible and here's what this
kind of horrible is like and here's what
you can do about it and here is a bunch
of other people who are also suffering
from it and they've recovered and so
with this kind of horrible there's all
these other things that you won't have
to worry about and that's really that
can be really helpful for people because
it narrows the universe of their
problems from all potential problems to
a potentially manageable set of finite
problems so so the so those are some of
the you some of the reasons for
diagnosis and some of the reasons why
diagnosis is useful so how do you
differentiate between having an actually
bad life and having depression make your
life bad
yeah well that's that's a good question
as well I think you can do that in a
multi-dimensional way technically
speaking so and so one of the ways I
conceptualize that is that you imagine
people's human life actually has a
fairly stable and identifiable number of
characteristics and so some of those are
you need to engage in trade with other
people and that in modern culture that
would generally be formalized as having
a career you need to have friends you
need to have an intimate relationship
you need to be embedded within a family
you have to conjure up something of high
quality that's productive to do with
your life outside of work you have to
attend to your physical and mental
and you have to regulate your use of
mind-altering substances like drugs and
alcohol there's other dimensions but
those are pretty decent as an initial
those serve the purpose quite nicely as
an additional schema so when you're
talking to someone in say in a clinical
intake the first thing you want to find
out is is the person functional on any
or all of those dimensions and the fewer
dimensions on which they're actually
functional the more they just have a bad
life and aren't depressed so if you have
no friends and you you have no
educational history and you certainly
don't have an educational history say
that's commensurate with your ability or
maybe you have no abilities you have a
patchy work history your family is an
absolute nightmare you you all you do
with your time is consume drugs and
alcohol and you have one or more serious
physical or mental health problems you
have a your life is has fallen apart and
now you're going to be suffering because
of that but to call that depression is
not useful particularly depression
technically speaking could spiral you
into a place where those things are more
likely but I would generally I think
it's better to conceptualize depression
as the mismatch between function and
emotion so if I did that approximately
six dimensional analysis with someone
and I concluded that hey well know if
this person has friends they may not be
seeing them right now because they're in
a bad state but they have friends and
their friends are good for them they
have an intimate relationship that's
functional they have their embedded
within a family that isn't too
pathological they have a job that in
principle serves the function of a job
but maybe that they could even be or had
been interested in etc that they're
feeling terrible and they're having a
difficult time getting out of bed I
would say well that increases the
probability that they should be
accurately conceptualized as a depressed
and then of course in in a real
situation the clinical presentation is
generally some mixture of those sorts of
things but it's very useful two distinct
one from another have I read aim Rand
and if I have what are my thoughts on
her philosophy objectivism of
Objectivism
um aim Rand is an ideologue and she's an
interesting ideologue because she's she
her ideology runs contrary to the most
prevalent modern ideology which is the
one that underlies political correctness
and so it's fun to read Ayn Rand
especially if you're hyper irritated by
political correctness because she
provides almost the perfect antidote to
that but and you know I have some
sympathy for her because she wrote in a
anti-communist vein and she had her
reasons because her family was chased
out of what became the Soviet Union by
the communists and if I remember
correctly had their property stolen and
all the terrible things that went along
with that but she writes heroes stories
of a certain type and the hero story is
the individual against the collective
roughly speaking and that's a perfectly
reasonable hero story and it's a useful
one but to think of that as the only
valid hero story in the constellation of
possible hero stories is a mistake
because you can also write a perfectly
good story where the collective is
relatively beneficial and it's the
collective and the hero against say that
dire forces of nature and that's also a
perfectly appropriate story so you might
say that there are circumstances under
which the attitude that a man puts forth
is accurate and salutary but to think of
that as covering the entire universe of
potential proper narratives is a big
mistake and usually ain't rands acolytes
do precisely that so Ariel says do you
think all presuppositions stem from
religion no what I think is that the
deepest presuppositions are identical to
religion that actually when we when we
talk about what constitutes religion
what we are saying
at the same time is that we're dealing
with the most fundamental
presuppositions that people make and the
thing that I find interesting about that
is that presuppositions are necessary
and the reason for that is that because
you have your a finite cognitive agent
you have extraordinarily limited
understanding in order to deal with the
world at all you have to act as if
certain parts of it are both understood
and stable like unchanging and those
elements that you treat as stable and
unchanging are at the deepest level are
your religious presuppositions whether
you think of them as religious or not is
irrelevant if you don't think of them as
religious or know that they're religious
all that means is that you don't know
anything about your presuppositions and
that you don't know anything about
religion and I learned that partly from
reading Carl Jung because one of the
things Jung posited was that the highest
value that exists in a person's
hierarchy of values is de facto
equivalent to their God now you know
that isn't often how people
conceptualize the idea of God or the
idea of value but it doesn't really
matter his point was that
psychologically a person's higher
highest value served precisely the same
function that a deity serves in you know
in a more explicitly religious society
so my experience too has been that that
if you're ever having a conversation
with someone that is really digging
towards the bottom of things
you the language that has to be used is
immediately religious because religious
language is the only language that's
kept capable of encapsulating the
phenomena that exists at the deepest
levels of analysis and so if that
language has never become necessary for
you all that means is that you've never
been in the sort of crisis that would
necessitate its use or that you don't
have the language at hand which is not
good Arianna says some researchers see
shame as something that is very
destructive
consensus seems to be that it is an
emotion that is always destructive do
you agree with this no that's absolutely
ridiculous and only modern psychologists
and probably social psychologists would
be foolish enough to even dare deposit
something so absolutely absurd
psychopathy and shamelessness are the
same thing so shame is a shame no
emotion is always destructive any
emotion taken to an extreme can be
destructive just like any value taken to
an extreme you know made into one thing
can be destructive so joy can be
destructive I mean people who are manic
are in some sense possessed by a radical
excess of positive emotion and they they
get incredibly impulsive and so and it's
terribly destructive I mean there's
almost no form of insanity that's more
destructive than mania people will go
out and spend all their money all their
family's money and well it engage in all
sorts of hyper optimistic interactions
with the world it will result in their
complete rude so you know people think
of happiness as an untrammeled positive
well if you think of happiness as
positive emotion which is partly true
because it's also the absence of
negative emotion if you think of
happiness as only a good then you have
no idea about the pathologies of
positive emotion and their manifold and
shame is like if you do something stupid
and destructive to yourself or to
yourself and the broader social
community
you should feel shame and you should pay
attention to it and you should learn
from it and if you're not capable of
doing that that then people should stay
the hell away from you because you're
shameless
and of course for most of Western
history and I don't know enough about
other forms of history to also make the
same comment to call someone shameless
was it was a tremendous insult it meant
that they didn't have enough sense to be
appalled by their own pathology and
theirs that's that's just not a good
thing at all
what makes a successful researcher
kurios curiosity intelligence diligence
you know those might be the personality
attributes and then you know being
embedded in a in the kind of social
network that supports research endeavors
is also extraordinarily necessary so I
guess you would add to that the
capability for extended collaborations
the ability to write is also
tremendously important I mean the place
that I see most graduate students fail
it's it's very rare that a graduate
student is incapable of formulating a
research hypothesis and they can always
discuss with other people what those
hypotheses might be and also infer the
next logical step merely by being
conversant with the relevant literature
they can also run experiments they can
generally also analyze them although
that starts to become a differentiator
but what kills graduate students is that
they they can't write and writing is
really difficult so you have to be able
to write and you have to either enjoy it
which means there's something wrong with
you or you have to be compelled to do it
and if you can't then you're gonna run
into trouble
let's see Christopher how do you feel
psychotherapy and psychiatry should work
together in curing psychological
disorders hmm well I presume that by
psychiatry what you're zeroing in on
there probably is the use of psychiatric
drugs because otherwise there's not much
distinction between psychiatry and
psychotherapy look if you have a serious
problem you should be very wary of
letting your a priori convictions
interfere with your health so you know
you hear very frequently that people are
all too easily made all too easily seek
help in the form of pills
and I just think that's wrong I don't
see any evidence for that at all
in my experience no one comes to a
clinician saying please give me a pill
for my mental illness so it will go away
first of all people don't want to think
even for a moment that they actually
have a mental illness second they
certainly don't want to be modified by a
pill and you know they generally feel
that that's an abdication of
responsibility and that they're
terrified of the side-effects and that
even if they do try it they want to get
off it as fast as possible and that it's
it's shameful that they have to be rely
on some sort of medication to begin with
and so like a lot of what you're doing
if you're dealing with someone who's
truly depressed is helping them come to
terms with the fact that a trial of an
antidepressant might be a useful thing
for them and that can take months that
can take years so I mean you don't want
to leave any stone unturned in your
search for health and psych cycle psyche
psyche at Rick medications can be very
useful and sometimes they're absolutely
necessary so for example your if you
have someone who is flirting with
psychosis or who's already entered a
psychotic state I think the general
consensus in the literature and I think
it's appropriate is that if you don't
facilitate their use of anti-psychotic
medication that what you're doing
borders on malpractice so now okay so
having said all that the probability
that a medication alone will be
sufficient to address the problem is low
partly because medications for
psychiatric disorders are much better
conceptualized as complex tools than as
curative agents you have to learn to use
them you have to learn what you have to
figure out what the drug should be you
have to figure out what the dose should
be you have to figure out
what time of day you're going to take it
and all of those are very complicated
decisions and require a fair bit of
experience to optimize and then you also
have to learn how you use those
medications while you're simultaneously
modifying whatever needs to be modified
in your attitudes or your life in order
to progress forward properly so the
optimal balance between the two is don't
say no to drugs two to rapidly because
you know you just might have the sort of
problem that's best addressed with a
psychiatric medication and that could
save you and your family not only
suffering but even death because you
know the probability of suicide with
serious depression is quite high and you
know trying to help someone who's
committed suicide because they're
depressed is extraordinarily difficult
so one of the things you really want to
do is stave that off but the drugs the
medications have to be used as tools in
a sophisticated way within a therapeutic
alliance because otherwise the
probability that their work is just
extremely low they're just too
complicated and they have too many
negative side effects like even with
antidepressants even when they work they
generally interfere with people's sexual
function so and that can be good if the
person who's depressed is also suffering
from something like premature
ejaculation because antidepressants are
good for fixing that but they produce an
ax or gazni ax which can be a real
catastrophe that that's more likely with
women and slow sexual response and in an
inhibited sexual desire and you know all
of that can be extraordinarily
problematic and that's just one of a
host of side effects that are that
psychiatric medications are likely to
generate so they're there they're like
chainsaws you know they're their tools
and they're useful but they're kind of
rough and you know if you use them
improperly they can do more damage than
good
how do you how should you decide between
being hard on yourself and giving
yourself a break
that's a good that's a very good
question
so one of the populations that I've had
some experience with has been I've
worked with a lot of lawyers and these
are usually very successful hard driving
ambitious people who are that way for a
variety of reasons often because they're
hyper conscientious as well as being
competitive but they're almost always at
least hyper conscientious and they have
other personality attributes and you
know one question that a person like
that addresses is well how hard should I
work and what am I just being useless
and the general answer to that isn't
well you should seek some appropriate
work-life balance because that's just a
bloody cliche if you're in a high highly
competitive job you're being chased by
your peers and your clients and the
marketplace to work flat out as fast as
you can all the time and so then the
question that you have to face is what
why under what conditions should you not
do that and I found PJ's thinking very
useful in formulating an answer to that
and the fundamental answer is you
shouldn't work so hard that you failed
you shouldn't work so hard that you
can't continue to work that hard so if
you're working 80 hours a week and say
you don't take a day off you will
eventually hurt yourself in a manner
that will make it impossible for you to
continue working 80 hours a week so
that's obviously counterproductive so
let's assume that your goal is instead
is to maximize your productivity and
then you might say well that means that
you have to take care of yourself
because otherwise you're gonna burn out
you're gonna get depressed you're gonna
get anxious you're gonna get exhausted
for which there's no diagnostic category
and that's gonna interfere with your
career so what you have to learn
how can you maximize your productivity
and often that means learning actually
how much work you can do and how much
leisure you need and how much you need
to involve yourself in activities that
are outside of work and one of the
things that happens to women
particularly when they hit their 30s and
I'll speak primarily about the lawyers
that I've worked with because my blog
worked with lots of female lawyers who'd
be made partners in large firms so
they've been very successful is that
they hit 30 or so they're through their
apprenticeship and they start to get
very disillusioned with their job and
part of the reason for that is is that
they make partner and then they find out
that the partners that they're
associated with have all the foibles
that are associated with normal people
and so there's a bit of a decline in
idealism but they also find out that
there actually is a lot more to life
than working like a Mad Dog for 80 hours
a week purely on legal issues which
might not even be that interesting in
and of themselves
so then they have to figure out well how
much time should be taken off and most
of the lawyers that I've worked with
have ended up working working fewer
hours but billing more hours so in fact
they got to have their take you needed
to they take a day off a week or two
days off a week they generally can't
work shorter hours because that isn't
how a profession like that works but
they can plan to take time off in the
future and do that quite regularly so
maybe a two-week vacation every three
months or every four months something
like that or a week every four months
and what they almost inevitably find is
that the boost they get from the
vacation increases their ability to
concentrate at work and makes them more
valuable as a practicing partner and so
you can think about it as a the attempt
to reach an equilibration state the
question how much should you work is
really the question how much can you
work productively so that you can have
the longest possible productive and
sustainable career and that means that
you have to set up your career in such a
way that it doesn't eat so much of your
life that you come to resent and hate it
because otherwise you'll bail out or
you'll act in a counterproductive manner
or you hurt yourself or so forth so I
would say for young people the way that
you figure that out is that you pick
something difficult to do when you work
yourself half to death doing it so that
you can figure out where your actual
limits are like your limits of
psychological and physiological
endurance and once you exceeded your
limits to pull back to the point where
that becomes sustainable and then that
way you're being hard on yourself to
test yourself out but you're also
allowing yourself the opportunity to
pursue what you're pursuing in the best
of possible health and with the highest
probability of continuing in a high
quality manner into the future what are
my views on euthanasia is the fact that
so many are against in a symptom of
individuals and societal aversion to
death or is it of the more practical
issues like consent morality oh well I
mean euthanasia is a complete nightmare
I mean you know the slippery slope from
it's okay if someone who's terminally
ill wants to die too let's empty out the
hospital's of all the people in it who
are no longer being socially productive
is like that's uh that's a road that
societies travel down one tiny little
step at a time
and so when you open up the specter of
euthanasia you're also opening up
endless cans of snakes
the existence of which many of which you
have no idea even exist now I kind of
think of euthanasia like torture so you
can imagine the situation imagine the
following situation and it's unrealistic
because no real situation is this
clearly bounded but we'll use it for the
sake of argument imagine that you know
for certain that someone in your custody
has planted an extremely high an
explosive device of extremely high
capacity in a football stadium and they
are going to detonate it unless you find
out where it is well you might say well
what interrogation techniques might be
ethically available to you in order to
conduct that investigation and I would
say and I know this is a flawed
philosophical argument but I'm just
using emphasis as a as an example high
levels of threat as an interrogation
technique you should be willing to
undergo prosecution for your actions you
can't expect to get a free ride even if
because the use of torture say in a
situation about it's so absurdly
socially dangerous that even if you
could make a case that it was ethically
justifiable in that particular
circumstance you should pretty much be
willing to give up the rest of your life
as a consequence of having participated
in that and I kind of think the same
thing about euthanasia it's like you
know what it Nietzsche said once that
nobody who's truly lived hasn't
experienced the necessity of killing you
know when to put this in simple terms
you know I had my dog put down in
February because he he was done and
allowing him to expire naturally seemed
to involve nothing but a lot of
unnecessary suffering so you can
certainly imagine the situation where
euthanasia seems like an the ethical
option but that doesn't mean that it
shouldn't be absolutely surrounded by
high thickets of illegality I mean
sometimes I think to do the right thing
you're required to break a law and be
punished for it now
apart from that I've also learned that
commenting generally on questions like
that is his almost always a mistake
because the devil is always in the
details so all right
is there a way to find your true passion
or is that just a cliche
what's definitely its Lachey and it you
know it's the sort of thing that
actually annoys me quite a lot about New
Age thinkers and I would more or less
put Joseph Campbell in that category I
think you can find what compels you and
what might enable you to live in a high
quality manner despite the suffering
that's associated with life I think you
can discover that and I think part of
the way you discover that is by watching
yourself and learning when it is that
you're meaningfully engaged you have to
notice that it's something that happens
to you in some sense rather than
something that you do you have to notice
when you're meaningfully engaged and
then you have to work to expand the
amount of time that you spend in that
state but I would also say that there
are moral requirements that go along
with that too because you might say well
what if you happen to be the sort of
person for example who finds torturing
small animals meaningfully engaging it
seems like that's a that's the sort of
meaningful engagement that you probably
don't want to expand so I would say that
if you're going to set up your life so
that you maximize your meaningful
engagement you have to there's a number
of other things that you have to do at
the same time and one of those is that
you have to get very clear about who you
are and what you're doing and so
although this would be grounds for a
much longer discussion I think that one
of the things that you have to do if
you're going to attempt to maximize
meaningful engagement is that you also
have to do such things as endeavor to
stop deceiving yourself and other people
in every way you possibly can
and part of the reason for that is that
if you engage in deception of any sort
you pathologize the structure both first
the structure of your being but you
could say you pathologies the structure
of your nervous system and then you
can't trust its reports so if your nerve
if you're going to rely on your nervous
systems reports of meaningful engagement
to guide your future activities you
better do everything you can to make
sure that you're not filling that
nervous system with the kind of garbage
that's going to make it malfunction and
give again give you false reports so I
think that moving towards meaningful
engagement has to be associated with
making truth your highest value because
otherwise you can't trust yourself as
your own guide I mean the Catholics have
struggled with this for a long time from
a theological perspective because the
Catholic position roughly speaking is
that human beings are so steeped in sin
that they can't trust their own
instincts in relationship to good and
evil and have to use the church and the
priesthood as an intermediary and you
know you can obviously have an argument
about that and of course Protestants
have historically done that but you got
to give the Catholics there dude it's
like people aren't pure by nature and
only trammeled in their vision by you
know sociological impediments they're
also corrupt beyond belief individually
and have to use society as a source of
value so if you're going to personalize
your life in some sense you better act
in a manner that makes you a reliable
guide so what time is it 2:30 well I
think maybe we'll call that a day
because I'm starting to get tired and
I'll start giving answers that not only
ramble but never actually come back to
the question so let's call that a day
and we'll take a look and see how it
worked